[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right good morning everyone welcome
to the stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
store and uh
okay i'll go ahead and say it the stall
is a place for us to coherent dialogue
about what matters most
at the nice set at this very moment and
today
we have peter wang returning for his
sense maker in residence series at the
stoa
on mental models
and each week peter comes in discusses
like a kind of a constellation of mental
models that he personally uses
last week was on relationships and this
is going to be kind of a continuation
on this subject with uh sprinkling in
some
metaphysical talk so um that being said
how today uh works if you have any
questions at any time when peter is
presenting his thoughts because peter
will present his thoughts at first just
type in the chat
uh i'll call you to meet yourself if you
want me to return your behalf
because this will go on youtube just
indicate that somewhere
um and we'll be here for an hour but we
might go over a little bit if
time uh allows it so that being said
i will allow peter to unmute himself and
take you in
good morning my friend good morning
and welcome everyone thank you for
joining me this morning um
let me go ahead and start the
screen share uh share screen oh
actually you have to enable screen
sharing for me
all right
screen share
and it is where to go there it is
great all right so
um those of you who are here
last time uh i talked about
relationships
and um in the first um on the first
session we did i talked about the
metaphysics of quality i'm hoping to
bring these things kind of
um together you know every week i talk
about something i try to relate it back
to
um what was talked about the week before
uh let's see if i can move this over so
i can see myself a little better great
so today i'm gonna be talking about
relationships uh a little bit about
networks uh
still relationships networks like from
last time but really talking about
change and hopefully have maybe a little
more time for for dialogue
last time i went fairly long talking
about a lot of stuff but
i have a slightly shorter slide deck
this time so
i'll networks and intelligence building
on last time um
i'll look at what what's called process
metaphysics and just spend a little time
talking about that
uh and then build building on that
relational process metaphysics and then
networked relational process metaphysics
so a lot of the word metaphysics uh
in there please don't be alarmed by that
hopefully it'll be more
um more accessible than this slide may
initially make it look
so again last time i took i talked about
you know
thinking about different ways of looking
at relationships just to recap
we generally in the vernacular think
about relationships as
the the connecting thing the thing
between two selves or two bodies or two
objects
we can say the sun and the moon are or
the sun of the earth our relationship
we can say that um all of us here on
this call on in the session are in
relationship to each other
but it's always viewed in sort of this
node link format we have nodes and
they're connected by links
um but the alternative view to look at
that is if we make the links themselves
the first class thing and the nodes are
actually not so much concrete structures
or atoms
but the links and the interactions are
the important things the binding energy
if you will
and when those come together and cohere
in a place or in a
region abstract or concrete um
that's what creates then a thing so
things substances
objects they are they are maybe
secondary and somewhat
a lot of the things are actually created
by the relationships
from the outside world and i also talked
about the sense of
um the sense of self and the sense of
agency freedom
what have you that sense of self and
sovereignty
emerges when we have um an inner
sort of society of relationships pushing
against an outer society
of relational pressures um and so this
is this is a way to think of the world
from a relational metaphysics if you
will as opposed to an atomic node
nodes with links kind of metaphysics now
um i wanted i wanted to this interesting
little story i saw
um come across on reddit which was this
little cat
that was riding the public buses um and
and he would uh
take like round trips and and the driver
would give him food he would sit on
passengers laps
uh and the driver would let him off i
had to stop
and so i so the thought experiment
besides this being a very heartwarming
adorable little story
the thought experiment is what is it
like to be this cat
remember you're a cat you don't know how
busses work they're just really really
big cats
that squish other cats right you don't
know what people are they're two legged
giant things
as far as you know there's cats they're
just inedible
and then and they're not mice and
they're not you know bugs i mean they're
they're not grass they're
but you don't have a model of like
anything in your world if just
try to reduce yourself down to a cat
brain you're this cat
and you step onto a bus the driver feeds
you i mean you don't know that as a
driver that has anything to do with
where the bus goes just
go on this bus you get fed you sit on
people's laps you get petted
no one eats you no one beats you and
then
um at some point you feel like there's
some attention on you and you
and the doors open and you get off and
it's right where you need to be
um really i would encourage you to
really try this i mean all of us we know
we're conscious and we think about human
consciousness all the time i'm sure
but try to think about what it's like to
be a cat
in this complex world of buses and um uh
you know metropolitan transport and
you're walking on this bus like a boss
and you're getting off this
bus like a boss uh
this is the reason i i prompt this is
because
there is an intrinsic amount of trust
that exists between this cat
and this organism of the bus right it
gets eaten it feels like it's getting
eaten by a bus and then it gets
regurgitated by a bus
and there are other you know agents
inside the bus that are relatively
harmless
my takeaway on this is that trust
is the generative kernel that allows for
relationships to arise and
um in abundant relationships with that
not dependent relationships so much but
but in this case it's more of a i guess
it's somewhat of a dependent
relationship
but at some point the cat must have
crossed a bridge of trust like indiana
jones right um
and he walks across that invisible
bridge spoiler alert by the way
but um you know there's there is this
kernel of trust that begins
the possibility of a relationship
and if it doesn't get violated if it
gets validated reciprocated
then a relationship can arise and and i
i think sort of just kind of taking a
swag at this i think
that this is true of essentially all
really solid
relationships is that there must be a
colonel
or a series of kernels or a continuation
of trust that exists and trust
is open and vulnerable this cat it could
go into a bus and who knows
as soon as that door closes ten pit
bulls to come rushing out the back and i
have a pit bull and they're not actually
that violent but you know
the point is that that cat is getting
eaten by a bus
it's trusting that it's not gonna die
right it trusts and
every time the driver lets it off at its
stop it
it validates right there's a validation
there and and i'm not going to talk
about
the other question which is a deeper
question of what is it like to be this
driver why does that human being driver
do this to the cat that's a completely
different question
but at least what it's like to be the
cat um
the other thing is that this of course
works across species we can think about
it in the concept of human relationships
but clearly
with our pets with animals that we love
and take care of
this is a thing right it also it doesn't
have to be animals
we tend to gardens now the gardens can't
really reciprocate much to us because
they move at a different
they have a different metabolic pace
than we do so do forests and so do the
rivers and so does all of the earth
but there is still um i mean when we go
to when we go to taking care of things
that have longer time span and deeper
more complex
dynamics than ourselves now we're the
cat
right so this is the thing to think
about
we're all cats on buses to some extent
we don't know if we're gonna get eaten
and whatever that door opens and we're
back magically at the doorstep of our
home
we feel blessed we feel validated right
the trust the trustal connection worked
so the other thing is that when we think
about the world purely from a
transactional perspective and from an
atomized interaction perspective of
transactions
trust is always the residual the residue
the remainder
that's just chopped off and forgotten
about it is the externality
in the social binding that's completely
ignored and this is the issue i have
when i meet people who are um and i do
have friends who are like hardcore
objectivists and
hardcore like just individuals atomized
sovereign interacting with individuals
we have no need to trust it's trustless
we have this wonderful blockchain thing
totally trustless and we can facilitate
all these interactions and it's like
actually trustless isn't the point the
point is to facilitate trust that's
where actually the generative value
happens
and so even in business and i'm i'm a
business person myself right i'm a ceo
and
a founder and entrepreneur and in
business my my experience has been that
the the i the con the word transactional
is a dirty word
right when i'm talking to somebody if
i'm talking to one of my uh executives
and we're
vetting a candidate and and she says to
me
well yeah you know they're experienced
but they're kind of transactional
that's a bad word that candy's not gonna
get hired
right so the idea in business
that it's all transactions is actually
looking at it from the wrong lens
in business business the way i always
talk about business is
transactions in the context of a
relationship that's the big difference
in business
and like when that's why you don't do
business with friends so to speak
because friends we don't have a ledger
of
our transactions if we're going to
transact let's say we all go in on a ski
trip somewhere or something
well we have a ledger we know exactly
the domain and the scope of activity
that we're going to have a transactional
accounting
but everything else we don't we don't
address on that and if you if you
look at friends who have drama i'm sure
you all have friends that have drama
that happens
look at it through this lens and i think
what you'll see is that oftentimes
the cause of drama is when people have
differing expectations
about transaction who's keeping it
ledger right what was relational what
was give and take
and if and you can't live in a world
humans cannot form a socialization
without some give and take right so this
is
again starting with the cat going to
relational
and really thinking about um the way we
build
networks and socializations that are
generative
is when we can trust with each other in
that relationship we can use trust to
build
these generative connections and they
are not transactional all those
transactions
can be conducted through them can flow
to them and be facilitated by them
they certainly can scale transactions
another great example of this is in
banking in the
um uh in the middle east there is
essentially a trust-based
peer-to-peer financial settlement and
credit system that they have
that is not like the sort of global you
know like um
you know the way would you swipe a
credit card to foreign country there's a
global series of banks and settlement
and everything talks over high-speed
internet
that's the way that we do it kind of in
the in the in the western world with
credit cards
but in the middle east um there's
there's essentially a
highly federated and decentralized um
credit facility across countries and
cities
and um it all works on a basis of trust
between all these different people it's
an ovation network
the word novation is not used very much
in the vernacular it's kind of a term of
art but it is uh it is the correct term
here they proxy trust they delegate
trust up to this
pure social network of lender clear
prime brokers
so um anyway
so completely switching gears um
ship of theseus how many people here are
familiar with the paradox of the ship of
theseus
a few people um so
i'll i'll walk through for those who are
not familiar it's a paradox that says
this actually comes from the greek
because you know uh there was a
um uh a story there from from plutarch
basically that
that said that basically um they have a
ship and every time some of the wood got
rotted or
decayed or got damaged they would
replace that piece of wood
and they put new stronger timbers in
this place right and so the
and so over time essentially every
single piece of wood on the ship had
been replaced
and the question is is it the same ship
right is the same ship and of course
because philosophers have too much to
eat
and too much time they argue back and
forth internally about this paradox
um and uh and it's a fun one it's a fun
one to try with kids it's a phone to try
just in you know if you're
at a cocktail party um it's a great way
to plumb the depth of thinking of
various people around you because it
does strike
us as quite a paradox i mean we as
people um
our atoms are being replaced all the
time
right we're decaying we're sloughing off
cells fluffing off atoms we're
boiling off if you if you leave an ice
cube on the counter
it melts into water and that water
eventually evaporates we
are just bags of water we're constantly
evaporating i'm drinking right now to
rehydrate
new atoms is this peter well no this is
a this is some
jar of guava nectar right but check this
out
now that just became peter body of
christ right this kind of thing
is so accessible and so much fun you
play with it and it all is centered on a
metaphysical
flaw and a metaphysical flaw is this
we in the normal let's say the normies
out there the muggles
see a world of static objects or a
static world of objects
some are little blobbies some are
collections of lobbies here's a grocery
bag filled with
a bunch of things each of those things
is themselves atomic maybe they're not
atomic but we can talk about the liquid
conceptually as a thing
we have a static world of objects
but kind of with the relational thinking
from last time and i talked about
relationships
between people but you can take it down
to the metaphysical level
right if we see the entire world
as um composed of overlapping
superpositions
of relationships then and it's a real
like mind bender to think about things
this way but if we think about it in
this
in this way then the ship of theseus
problem
disappears and i'll give you a concrete
example of of this kind of
thing which i always love um holograms
now most of you have probably seen a
hologram if you have like a visa credit
card you see a little hologram printed
or
you've gotten you know maybe stickers uh
maybe even a science museum and you
looked
and the the thing about a hologram
that's different than a photograph of
course is
if i take a photograph that captures one
perspective if i turn the photograph
sideways i mean i don't see a different
perspective
of the thing inside the photograph now
with our tablets nowadays and our
smartphones
we get augmented reality things that are
really cool right i can sort of turn the
thing around it actually changes the
perspective of the camera
in the virtual space but um
but but of course static pictures don't
do that take a picture i print it out i
look at the picture different angles
it's the same point of view
in the picture itself holograms are not
this way holograms
when you bounce light on them they
project a light field
such that if you move your head
around that light field you actually see
different perspectives so
what's shown here on the left is this is
the hologram of a mouse
and when you look from different
directions at the projection of the
hologram
you see different views on the mouse as
if there was a real virtual mouse back
there
now if you i don't know how many of you
have then actually gone and looked at
what a hologram actually looks like
you know because they bounce laser light
off of the hologram
itself and it produces this light field
you look at the actual hologram looks
like
just a bunch of overlapping like
it doesn't look like anything i mean you
look at you're like what is that it's a
bunch of like it almost looks like noise
but what it is is extremely extremely
tiny
um imprints of the light field itself
the diffraction of the light field
it captures it and then when you when
you shine
a coherent light on that light field
again it reconstitutes
so it's like taking a slice of the light
field and without getting into the
physics of optics and all these other
things
um suffice to say that uh when you do
come across the word holographic
uh in in maybe um
in technical literature when they or in
philosophy
the idea of a hologram is that we're
capturing multiple points of view
and something about like the
three-dimensional aspect of the stuff
of the light field we're capturing that
and projecting it in
this this little miniature thing that
the idea of the smaller thing captures
a lot of the structure and detail and
multiple perspectiveness of
of this larger reality holography right
hologram
um and so likewise here uh i started
drawing this thing i bring up the
holograms because it reminded me a lot
of what an actual hologram looks like
it's
like diffraction rings all like tied
into each other
so if we look at the world not as a
static world of objects
but as these overlapping worlds of
relations
um then you you can
uh the the way i talk about it is that
when when we when we think about um
the world is not consisting of of atomic
um substance but we see everything as a
continuum
in energy in space right uh if you
really go and i
mentioned this last time in quantum
mechanics if you go to the
um quantum mechanical fundamentals of
atoms
they're not really a solid atom thing
it's it's quantum mechanical wave
functions
that because of measurement because of
interaction because whatever else
they they form a spatially localized
region
but otherwise you model it uh in
in as a continuum field
if you think about the world as
continuum field like this
then um then you realize that that
things are not bounded so if you look at
the world as
atoms you tend to think of them as being
bounded in space
but here's the other thing you tend to
think of them as static and bounded
in time when you think about the world
as
these waves you intuitively don't think
of a wave as frozen
it's weird to think of a wave like if
you drop a rock in a pond
and the waves are rippling and imagine
the waves as being stopped
seems super unnatural it is natural for
us to think of wave phenomenon
as being evolving waves themselves are
just wave fronts that are evolving if
you will right
so when we go to a wave or continuum a
medium view of
a medium based way of looking at the
world
it leads us naturally to what's called
process metaphysics or process
philosophy
and um and the idea here is that it is a
different point of view
than say the aristotelian view of the
world which says the world consists of
objects
objects of fundamental substances we now
know that there's 118 or whatever it is
fundamental
types of atoms that we found um and
atoms are consisting of these
fundamental particles and it's like all
this stuff
but it's all a world of static
construction process philosophy
turns us completely around and says
actually everything is changing
all the time there's actually nothing
that is just is
everything is changing all the time um
and our only ability to perceive
static objects is because we insist on
tracing causal narratives through the
world
so we say well here's a thing and when
this thing has this dynamicness to it it
knocks on this thing
and that thing does these things and my
need and my
um intentional trace of causality
through all these overlapping wavefronts
of energy and possibility
that need for that narrative is actually
what creates metaphysical reality
right and and and this is again just
super this is a a younger me
listening to myself pontificating like
this would say hold up peter if i were
to throw a brick at your face there's no
process velocity involved there's some
hard substance there in that brick
right come on stop what crack are you
smoking
and and it's true that a brick falling
on my toe or hitting my face would hurt
and there is substance there um uh but
you know pain as the buddhists say pain
is just attachment right
um if i'm not attached to my face having
to be
a a piece like this no actually that's a
joke um the the
the point is that the if you really get
into the details of what happens at the
physical level in the physics
you see that there's a lot of truth to
this even in the mathematical
formulations
when you zoom out and you look at
dynamics of human civilization
there's also a lot of truth in this all
of how many of you have used the word
france in conversation
probably all of you at some point in
your life have used the word france but
there is no france is there
right which france are you talking about
historically through time if you talk
about france right now
the border of france and i'll get to the
boundary in just a second but you're not
just talking about the space within
france you're also probably referring to
french culture which is a timeless thing
emerging from all the french people
french people living in
france and all the expats you have all
of these other things that have a
franceness to them
now none of us i think would deny that
france exists and yet
as soon as you ask that question you're
like well but what does it mean for it
to exist it's not a brick
right um and as soon as we start
creating these hard boundaries
in our metaphysics like well a brick is
real but france isn't
uh you know an atom is real but you know
i don't know
you know christianity isn't when you
start approaching the world with this
metaphysical frame
you end up with all sorts of faux
paradoxes like the ship of theseus
that only exists because your frame is
broken not because the world
uh has any weirdness to it right
everyone is everyone in france
knows what france means and everyone
lives in france as if they live in
france not as if they're all just
delusional
about living in france so the idea of
going to alternative metaphysics like
this
is to create a greater synthesis of
phenomenon and relational things
so um and even an atom just to make just
to kind of do a little more like science
hour here
um i don't know how many of you know
this but uh
we we've all learned in school there's
the proton and the neutron and they're
in the nucleus of the atom
and there's a bunch of electrons you
know either you might have drawn the
picture of the orbitals but really
they're kind of these clouds of
electrons
right not a difficult concept certainly
any
physics chemistry engineering student at
any university in the world would agree
with this assessment of the atom
however proton and neutron
and electron well they were discovered
different times
and they have vastly different kinds of
properties to them to the point where
you almost question their metaphysical
weight electrons well do they really
exist i don't know it's like because
because there's a there's a wave there's
a probability wave we can't even talk
about where this thing is
until you hit it with something else and
then it becomes localized depending on
what you're hitting it with and it's
like
what other thing in the world you know
france doesn't vary depending on which
angle i come at france from right
like it doesn't like there's other
things that are actually like france is
more real than electrons
to some extent and then you look at
protons and neutrons well protons okay
the protons of mass and charge and
they're quite heavy this were all
you know the most of the mass neutrons
are also massive just like protons that
have no charge they're intellectually
neutral
protons how long does a proton last
can a proton be destroyed or created
well in a super in a
in a super collider you can you can
destroy them and you know knock them
into each other and get little bits out
of them
but in general a proton will stay around
for infinite number of like infinity
ever forever
naturally protons just kind of are
always there neutrons
which are also the same masses protons
that are electrically neutral
they have a half-life of 10 minutes
they remember tell you that in high
school neutrons
decay naturally in the space of
not even a television sitcom episode so
here's something that lasts for the
lifetime of the universe here's some of
the decays instantly and here's
something else that floats around the
bubble of probabilities until we
probe it with another bubble of
probabilities and that is the building
blocks of matter
so when we talk about metaphysics as
being all like oh it's too hand wavy and
of course you look at worlds in many
different ways but what does it mean
the actual fundamental metaphysics we
use to kind of construct
physical reality when you get down to it
it's actually kind of left up it's kind
of messed up
it's not nearly as solid as you might
think it is so
when we talk about process philosophy
again to the point of the
holographic view of the world or looking
at the world as relationships
there's nothing wrong i guess i'm just
saying this almost as an apologia to say
there's nothing
wrong with taking alternative frameworks
it's like taking you know an
axis and rotating it and looking at the
world through different axis there's
nothing wrong about it there's nothing
more fake about it
it's actually a really useful and more
unifying way to look at the world
as processes as becoming as
as waves and as relationships colliding
with each other
and furthermore the static world of
objects that static metaphysics
static object metaphysics it has nothing
to say
about mimetics about the dynamics of
human socialization
this other one scales up and down and
across all different kinds of domains
so one uh
another uh just to really put a you know
not to find a point on it
but uh talk about the you know the
measure of electrons and does france
exist
this is a picture of the coastline of
california it's not on fire
but it is the coastline of california
and here's a really fun question again
another great cocktail sort of party
dinner dinner table sort of like
thing how long is the coast of
california
this is a question of physics this is a
question of reality
right this is not peter going off on
weird metaphysics this is a very like we
all kind of
well to the extent that we acknowledge
there exists a thing as california
and we bound it and we to think not to
the extent that we acknowledge that
there's water and there's liquid in
solid state
and where in the the sand you know
constitutes the boundary
there is a length of coastline surely
there exists a coastline of california
that does exist right at some point
you're in the ocean at some point you're
not
and surely it has the length i can
measure anything in the world why can't
i measure the length of the coastline of
california
but here's the here's the other this is
this is another fun ship of theseus
thing right
the length of the coast of california
depends on the scale at which you
measure it
if i measure the coast of california
with a yardstick
i get a different answer than if i
measure it counting
every millimeter of jaggy if i zoom out
to an aerial view and i'm measuring it
by kilometers
i get a different measure none of those
answers are correct
and yet none of them are wrong either
right what this is highlighting is that
the very concept
um it's it's you know what's the issue
here i mean
how many of you have i don't know how
many of you thought about this but there
is there's actually not an issue
here except for our metaphysics and our
sort of philosophy of science right
the california does not have a problem
its coastline does not have a problem
the ocean is not confused about this the
sands are not confused
what's confused is that the concept of
length is not a purely objective measure
right
length itself is actually a projection
of subjectivity
how do we want to measure how do we want
to perceive it that gives us a readout
that readout is contextualized by how we
measured it and
as long as we carry that context forward
we can do a lot of interesting and
useful things
if we lose that context and say nope
there is this objective thing that is
the length of california
there is objective truth here is the
length of california i don't why are you
talking about yardsticks and metaphysics
there is of course meta a california
with a coast and it has a length
done if you take that kind of view of
the world you're just going to be
confused by paradoxes left and right
because again to whitehead's point here
causality causal narratives all of the
ways that we look at objects in the
world and their relationships to each
other if we view them as static
and not as dynamic things that are
becoming if we view them
as as atomic things substances that
bounce
against each other and not as
overlapping waves of possibilities and
of energies and
and and reality and dynamics then
we have paradoxes all over the place
because because it's our own measuring
tools our
mental models that create the paradox
just like the measuring stick here
creates the paradox so to make this more
visual
an atomic or spatial view really talks
about beings
in fact we use that term beings it's a
being it's an object it's a thing
but a process view views everything as a
snapshot of becoming
all beings are snapshots of becoming and
everything is constantly becoming so
physics any of you who learn physics you
learn about objects you learn about
their emotions you learn about energy
and dynamic in fact we call it
kinematics which is the motion of
objects
and dynamics the study of energies that
lead those objects and systems to evolve
in time to the way they do
and and that's i mean that's what
physicists do those are the actual terms
we use
so in physics we're based on uh
you know physics in the modern era is
based on a metaphysics of static things
that do have dynamics to them but the
dynamic-ness is always
about certain capturable properties of
the static thing
the process view is a different
metaphysics and it is actually more
resonant with like the quantum
mechanical view of the world
and maybe future physics to come will be
based on process metaphysics
so that we can always talk about uh
things
uh these four-dimensional flows in fact
there's a term for this called
four-dimensionalism
and this whole body of thought which is
that we we should stop looking at things
the static things that evolve in time
and actually look at everything as
processes that interact and create
coherent zones in space and in time
um and this this framing of being or
becoming
um is uh is a term used by uh
you know i stole it from ilya
priyogine's uh the title of his book
um he is a nobel prize winner very very
um
very very smart person and when you look
at complexity and chaos when you look at
dynamical systems
when you see physicists that study
things like um
you know uh laminar flows non-linearity
or spin glasses metastable things um
people study that kind of stuff they're
right they're they're basically probing
through the holes of the current
metaphysics the original metaphysics
and they're always having to look at
things from kind of this process and
dynamical view
so all that being said if we can layer
in the stuff that i was talking about
the first
um in the very first session about the
metaphysics of quality
where we view individuals as having a
physical and biological social
intellectual aspect
if you don't view if you don't look at
that layer cake as a static layer cake
but as overlapping flows i mean each one
existing on top of the other i mean
they're not
actually disjoint like this i drew them
this way but but recognize this sort of
like
one is higher frequencies on top of
lower frequencies on top of even lower
frequencies but it's all one body of
water it's all you you're a bag of water
right
so if you add the metaphysics of quality
to this kind of process metaphysics view
you realize oh oh i'm actually
multiple different kinds of overlapping
dynamics evolving in time
and each part of the self has a
different rate of evolution
each part of the self as it evolves in
time interfaces with the other parts and
and maybe resonates with it or jostles
against it um
which is you know i love the one of the
terms i love from stoic practice about
the integral self right mindfulness and
the wholeness of being the embodied self
is is essentially another way of saying
make sure your intellectual part is in
resonance with your social part
is in resonance with your biological and
physical all of it
moves together you gotta have good diet
good exercise good rest
uh learn how to how to trust and
love authentically right and then um
harness your attention be mindful of
your attention all these things
is making sure that one part of these
ways don't get don't start bubbling so
fast
it evaporates and you lose mass and you
lose coherence with the rest of the you
because all of you is becoming in time
so
here's the other thing uh i i lightly
touched on this before
when i said that uh in a process
metaphysics we view everything as flows
of constant becoming
and static objects or any kind of static
approach towards if we approach
something from a static perspective
we're bounding it in time and space okay
but we we we can form
relationships with each other i mean you
are not me
and even if we hold hands and touch even
if we're in an embrace
we're still two distinct objects right i
mean at a at a very visceral and a very
accessible intuitive level that seems to
be the case
but when we
look at so there's a relationship still
somewhat between two distinct objects
but if we think about the self
as not just localized in space but
localized in time
then we can talk about our relationship
to our future
and our relationship to our past and we
do this anyway i mean you don't have to
go through metaphysics to understand
that people talk about their past and
their futures right that's something we
do
but if you think about it this way and
you decompose or deconstruct a little
bit and look at the different
frequencies of being and frequencies and
rates of change of your
of the different layers of yourself you
can see that you relate to
different aspects of yourself in
different ways so
in the past we have memory we have the
memory of ourselves
we have even subconscious memory and
subconscious trauma right you get
together the freudian stuff
and and then we also have a future
potential
and we interface not just with our own
past selves and futures but with each
other's
and with different aspects of each
other's if i'm only interested
in someone's biological future that's
like literally
what we mean when we say something is
objectifying and it's ugly
right no no no one no one wants to get
objectified
and what is objectified means it means
that you're getting reduced from this
complex
of this of multiple overlapping evolving
becomings
into a single aspect you you get you
bottle into a single aspect
you're objectified and then probably
transacted with
as an object so when we
um talk about interacting with our past
selves and our future selves
these are all different lanes or
different um aspects we can be
relating to ourselves in a lot of
coaching a lot of therapeutic and
therapy sort of work is in helping
people
get a current set of things in resonance
with each other you know if they're if
they're
if they're broken if they're hurt uh
broken is a sorry kind of a derogatory
term but
um if people are feeling a lot of pain
and caring a lot of trauma then parts of
them are stuck
other parts are trying to get forward
and none of it's in resonance
if you can get in resonance by showing
that they can actually
break with the past a little bit or they
can understand the past in context
that they're not stuck in the past they
don't have to carry it forward every
moment
that's a very um standard practice in
in in therapy and coaching right
so this idea of seeing yourself as a
multi-layered thing evolving in time
relating to yourself in this way and
relating to others in this way
then leads to the topic of love
and i think my my sort of working
definition
of love is when we
are taking a vested interest we are
actively putting energy
into helping some other entity
or collection of process flows
reach their future full integral
potential
and we put energy into that we trust
that that energy
will well i mean we don't even need to
trust the recip reciprocity of it
but we're putting it into it not because
of a reflection we get out of it or
something we transact out of it
but because uh we're just putting energy
into this other system
so we're taking our energy and our
essence and putting it into some other
system
uh donating contributing helping the
other system achieve resonance
and and maximal optionality as it
evolves
forward in time and then a mutual loving
relationship is of course when two
people or objects or
whatever zones of confluences of of
of processes when they do that for each
other so
anyway that is process metaphysics
that's a bunch of
a whole bunch of metaphysics probably
more than you care for on a friday
morning
um and now i will stop for questions
all right uh so start dropping your
questions
in the chat have a have a cue in front
of them if you want to uh
speak it and also if you just want to
share a statement with peter or the
group just maybe put an ass
too and then we can we can go uh do that
someone did say
i'll read this uh okay peter wayne is
lovable
thank you we are all lovable but i
appreciate i appreciate you
thank you very much so i i'll start with
the first question um
you mentioned something about normies
right and uh yeah
like normies they're lovable too they're
lovable too
but like you know normies got a norm and
then the norm right there is
you know the contrast process philosophy
like a static philosophy
and there's sort of like an epistemic or
i should say metaphysical violence like
subtly when you interact with someone
who is like projecting a static
philosophy on you
so i'm wondering if you have any
tactical
mental models in order to ground
yourself in a process philosophy and
encourage it in others
and i was returning to what you said
about trust and love
um like there's something that i'm i'm
terming as the hemingway heuristic
like ernest hemingway said if you want
to find out if someone's trustworthy
trust them
um right and it relates to the pygmalion
i think effect where if you just kind of
uh view someone in a certain light it
influences them to become that way
so i'm curious if you have any thoughts
on that and if you have any tactical
mental models in order to kind of like
you know deal with that
yes so let me walk backwards right so
the last thing you said was the
the the pygmalion um thing uh so
interesting right because this is
related to the uh
when i talked about celebrity culture um
and the the fact that our
uh current media systems or or
communication technologies created
the concept of celebrity and even the um
the uh the song video killed the radio
star right by adding a video aspect
to media we removed the
primality and the primacy of sound and
made it all about image and aesthetic
so um we people do
deeply understand or they've perceived
some of these phenomena they don't
understand it but they
perceive some of these things um so
but that thing about um the pygmalion
thing um
let me see the right way to talk about
this okay so when you
look at this picture here um back to the
screen share here
right um the
celebrity is a is very much not even a
double-edged sword celebrity is
crushing right every celebrity has
talked about y'all don't understand what
it's like to be famous
you can't walk down the street without
people coming to you with an expectation
of who you are
so that's pygmalion times you know 10
million right 10 million followers
they're all telling you however not that
eliza doolittle you could pass off as
the
you know whatever some duchess or
whatever of some you know
transylvanian thing you are a gutter
snipe
right hey i saw you on the gutter side
video watch your gutter snipe
right this is the oracle like i think
about the character of like urkel
as the is like he can never get away
from being urkel so this is the same
thing that that pigment
how we look at things now here's the
thing
if we don't ever interact with something
we just perceive it and that's just our
perception and
our subjectivity that doesn't matter
there's no impact on that thing or
person or whatever at all
but if we all socialize with each other
and we create in the social field an
understanding of what that avatar is or
that explanation is
now we're doing a thing to that person
right even if we actually ourselves
don't directly talk to that person
so there's kind of like social media has
created this in just you know uh all
over the place it's really terrible
um so the the youtuber generation will
figure this out at some point but but
this is the doom that's coming to them
um but when it comes to tactically
addressing
people with um uh who are stuck in a
static
metaphysics you can well you can
probe i mean depending how long you have
to interact with them uh if you're
really sitting down for a long
conversation you can start with the ship
of theseus
and just get them uh confuse them
because confusion at least is honest
right
what's true about a trump voter that's
solidly maga solidly like just
fu on trump uh is that they're not
confused at all
they're not confused at all they know
for damn sure exactly
uh why he is great for america and why
you hate america if you don't vote for
him right
so when you talk to people if you can
get them into that liminal moment with
confusion
that's great so take these two tools
take the coast of california
um ask them to measure the california
coast of california ask them if the ship
of theseus is still the ship of theseus
and and if they say well that's just
that's just a bunch of philosophy
nonsense then i would say try to on your
feet
adapt that to something that's more
accessible to them because
the great thing about well what i think
the correct metaphysics here is with
process metaphysics the great thing
about it is that
it's accessible everything in the world
changes
everything in the world has this
character to it if you look at it across
the right time scales and sample it with
the right frequency
so um the tree in the backyard
right um everything you can look at
and use the starting point to talk about
process metaphysics
um and and to get them the goal
is to use these things confuse them and
get them thinking about
how things change how they themselves
process change
and isn't it the case that the world is
always changing
because most of the time when people use
subject or static metaphysics as a
defensive mechanism in particular um
it's it's to defend it's to defend a
um it's it's always to defend a
worldview defend a way of doing things
um it usually there's a sense of
conservatism and entrenchment
i feel like um as opposed to a dynamic
zen
aikido master kind of like flowing with
the things as they change
so anyway i would encourage i would
encourage that
does that actually answer your question
are those is that helpful yeah yeah
it reminds me of vent cat's grey-pilling
term um
like the idea of giving people great
pills to get them in that liminal
state um and someone in the chat says
that could be uh you know
anxiety invoking and uh i wonder if
there's a way you can do it in a i don't
know
a delightful way yeah yeah well i think
the coast of california is relatively
approachable because
uh and you know or something to that
form think about
uh other kinds of things where our
measurement reveals and actually you
know what
uh the way to find something like this
is look for complexity
because humans naturally do not deal
with complexity we
always overlay complexity with
metaphysical or epistemic boundaries and
wrap it up and say well here's the thing
um um so anytime
you find or think of something as
complex not complicated a watch is
complicated
a cockroach is complex right um so
look not for complications because those
are decomposable into smaller bits that
are all then static moving
with with very linear and rigid
dynamism but complex things there's a
sloshiness to them it could be a block
of birds flying a murmuration of birds
right
all kind of swooping around look for
complexity
and and find something there that could
amuse and delight them
you know delight and confusion they
could go hand in hand
um so let's turn to the the questions uh
kyle you had a question
sorry i couldn't find my mute um so it
it i was kind of riffing on this in the
chat i'm not sure if it makes sense but
you all can tell me if it does or
doesn't um
i've never made the connection before
that kind of the process versus static
mindset that you're talking about
uh fits into what carol dweck's done on
fixed versus growth mindsets kind of
from a psychological perspective
and and so i was thinking about back to
the cat
um that there's there has to be some
individual level agency towards the
choice of being in a trusting
relationship
yes and yes and and so that's the cat
that's obviously cat but
mutual trust is at least dyadic if it's
not more complicated than that
right right it is pebbles in a pond all
these overlapping waves right
you just drop two pebbles in but we live
in a world of at least seven half
billion really interesting pebbles
right so um yes
so the individual i guess what i'm
trying to get at is what are the
necessary and sufficient conditions
at the individual level for the choice
to engage in trust
so uh okay let me share my browser
screen with you
um so i don't know how many people here
on the call are familiar with um
whitehead but this guy he's a
mathematician
who was trying to formalize the entire
structure
of um of like analytic philosophy and
mathematics and
in fact uh you know girl incompleteness
for those of you programmers probably
familiar with this
uh was was sort of a rejection of some
of the stuff he was working on but he's
a very famous like
hardcore like philosopher nerd kind of
guy and
and he his articulation of what is this
ultimate principle
believe it or not it's creativity
for him the ultimate abstract principle
of actual existence is creativity
and we ourselves our expression of the
aggregate creativity of the trillions of
atoms that comprise us
and billions of cells and our societies
and our cultures and our
and our groups and our families in our
relationships
are the expression of something
and nothing you might as well call it um
in a sense again the free will versus
determinism paradox
right also is a is a faux paradox
because it's rooted in static
i got static objects i got causal laws
for them where the hell is the
determinism right you're just a pile of
static objects and
if you turn around to process it's like
well no the static object projection in
the envelope
is itself just a tool you use to help
you know
to help your predictive theories along
but there's plenty of places where those
theories fall apart and you have to use
like statistical mechanics
there's nothing deterministic about that
at all so um
so if you can look through all of it
it's it's creativity and this ties to
my first session about robert persig and
metaphysical quality remember
static versus dynamic quality every
level of patterns
you can see there is a dynamism an
energy in them
that's the that's the thing that springs
the thing forward right the ratchet
picture
if i go back to the diagram here for
those who were not here for that
um session share
and it's this guy the
the ratchet right and
people's mindsets the conservative
mindset of the the the fixed mindset
from
dwight's formulation that's the two and
it's it provides friction from number
one rotating but also keeps from
slipping back
that's you know what my life coach calls
protection right you're trying to like
protect yourself from hurt from pain
from
chaos and degeneration but
something drives one what is the spring
coiled up
what is god's hand turning one forward
that isn't everything it's in every atom
it's in every beetle it's in every human
it's in every state it's in france if
you believe france exists
it's everywhere there's a creative
energy in france for sure right
and so there is this there is a
a universal cosmological principle
and i talked about this in that first
session as well that the second law of
thermodynamics
is all about the action of two when that
forward driving is is done when we have
a closed system
if there ever is such a thing as a
closed system which there never is but
if we define a closed system
within the closed system things will
decay to energy things will slip back
things will go backwards
and all the physics in equilibrium
science is based on building theories
and models and
analytical equations for that very
little of science and math
is obsessed with what happens when
there's energy when there's new and
excessive free energy coming in
what happens and in all cases new things
happen
right things grow things create new
structures um whether you're taking a
cello bow on the side of a plate of
metal with sand on it whether you just
put a bunch of
random chemicals into a pot and put
under the sun for a few billion years
life happens and creativity blossoms
across the across every level
of the metaphysics
all right thank you kyle uh deef you had
a question
um i've been jumping different comments
here and there
but uh part of the way my my mind works
is try to
integrate multiple perspectives and try
to bring up the essence
your add-on of the creativity and
artistic views sort of
the artistic view to create to capture
the divine in the
most concise and precise language
or art art and then so one potential
limitation is that by
your medium of communication is very
static pictures
and words and mental models
isn't that a bit of a limitation to try
to encourage somebody else to have a
more
time scaling waveform of perspective
uh because western models is just linear
time so you're automatically
communicating by
fractionating time from that cause and
effect instead of a
cyclical or a nested layer of time right
or superposition right yeah so language
and communication by
this medium you're communicating is
reinforcing
uh materialist atomized type
perspective yeah well i'm going to quote
a very unlikely person to make an
appearance here in the stoa
donald rumsfeld the former secretary of
defense for the united states
uh famously quoted i believe you go to
war with the metaphysics you have not
the metaphysics you wish you had
right so uh or maybe that wasn't quite
his quote but that's essentially my
variant on it
um to be completely honest and i really
appreciate everyone's engagement and
questions here
um i've been thinking about this stuff
for a while some of these things are go
back 20 years when i was an undergrad
right
in in college some of these things are
relatively new that i've discovered in
the last few years
as i've gone deeper and deeper on the
medics um and in the modern
technological society
um but this is the first context where
i've actually sat down and tried to
elucidate
all you know paint a picture of many of
these things for any kind of an audience
that wasn't just like a couple of
buddies over a beer so um
so you know i think you're right i think
what would be great
is if i could assemble when i talk about
murmuration
right it'll be a narrative over a video
showing actually a flock of birds
forming murmuration
right that we could actually have um
visual experiences
that show this and then when i talked
about overlapping versus distinct
it's it's um a lot of it for me
uh the model of communication
um is is sort of like music
is super positional music and taste are
the you know flavors and taste
music and taste are the two things that
we directly
viscerally encounter every day that are
intuitively superpositional
everything else tends to be more
cartesian more distinct more
you know um sequential and linearized
and atomic
and so um it would be great
to have contrasts of those in a very
accessible way to show people
imagine if we had to sequentialize music
and it wasn't super positional
imagine you know like you can actually
tell a story around this not just
imagine but showing people and letting
them hear the sounds
i think that'd be a very powerful way to
get this kind of thing to make this more
accessible
um to a larger audience i agree with you
deep this is definitely a limitation of
the medium and i
uh but it's also kind of a an audience
that will bear with it right that will
that will tolerate the medium
and the limitations so but you're aware
of it sounds like you're aware of the
limitation of the media man
yes the best thing is we all get the
other person and we walk through the
woods and i point out things
that are illustrations of this principle
to show these to show the universality
of some of these things
right that would be the ideal thing
okay good deal
cool um we are approaching the
hour so maybe it'd be prudent to wrap up
and i don't see any uh see a lot of
statements but i don't see any
uh questions uh or i can't tease any out
um so peter do you have any kind of
closing thoughts or you want to set us
up for
next week um well i guess i would like
to get a
sense from people like uh if this was if
this was um
you know useful or if like this was like
um
is it the right level of what people
want to hear or is this um
a little too abstract or do you want
like more like what i don't know what
the
i don't know like do you want me to just
talk about mimetics i talk about x and
and whatnot um next time i could talk
about um
uh oh shoot the model of communications
i mean maybe that's the right thing i
mean it would be
maybe that's not to talk about next time
if folks are down with that
yeah um people are saying this has been
amazing
and my my preference when i when i
invite someone to the store is to talk
about something that really resonates
with them
and then there's like a there's like a
bias filtering effect that people will
gravitate towards that
to this session and i'm particularly
really loving these sessions i've been
writing my journals about them
okay um and just you know the idea of
putting all these mental models and
putting them beside each other just
creates all these rich connections
and that alone despite whatever memetic
artifact gets produced from this that
alone is such a rich process
and you're so good at it so um yeah i'm
very grateful and that nice thank you
well grateful for you being here yeah
well this is this is just so much fun
for me
and it's a highlight of my week to get
to just actually sit down and talk about
some of these things that are near and
dear to my
heart and to my mind um and so let's
let's see it up for next time
let's really go and talk memetics and
talk about them starting with the model
of communications
talk about the music boxes and the
sculptures and
go from there beautiful
beautiful all right peter uh thank you
so much to the fourth and final session
of the mental model series same time uh
this week we'll talk about memetics
communication
um for upcoming events we have a few
today we have a collective presencing
which is sort of a
intersubjective practice that you know
we get to practice this relationality
and then have a felt sense of the
contours of it
um and then it sets at 12 p.m eastern
time
and then at 3 p.m eastern time nina
power is coming in to talk with rachel
haywire and raven connolly
and the philosopher queens series which
should be pretty cool
uh we have a socratic social tonight uh
if you just want to
you know have random encounters and have
deep talks uh
that happens at uh 7 p.m eastern time
maybe gray is going to be hosting this
one
um that being said feel free to check
out all the events at the store
i'm just like trying to collect links
here and then you can support us on
patreon right there if uh you'd like to
support the essence of what we're doing
here at the store
that being said peter everyone thank you
so much
thank you everyone have a great uh great
weekend